Fred Harvey collection, 1896-1945
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Fred Harvey hotels collection, 1896-1945
AZ 326
Fred Harvey (Firm)
The Fred Harvey collection documents the business activities of the Fred Harvery Company. The collection consist of approximately 2,000 black and white photographs depicting exterior and interior views of hotels, eating houses, railroad stations and news stands operated by Fred Harvey; a scrapbook;two guest register books; blueprint plans for news stands;a ledger book records some Grand Canyon operations, 1906 to 1933; and correspondence.
8.3 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Historical Note
Fred Harvey (1835-1901) began a partnership with the Atchison, Topeka and Santa Fe Railway in 1878. In 1889, the Railway gave Harvey exclusive rights to manage and operate his eating houses, lunch stands, and hotel facilities upon the Santa Fe's railroads west of the Missouri River. The Harvey Houses took pride in their first class food, service, and cleanliness.
Organization
This collection is organized into three series:
Series I: Photographs, No Dates
Series II: Correspondence, 1896-1944
Series III: Supplemental Material
Scope and Content Note
This collection includes approximately 2,000 black and white photographs depicting exterior and interior views of hotels, eating houses, railroad stations and news stands operated by Fred Harvey. States represented are Arkansas, Arizona, California, Colorado, Illinois, Kansas, Mississippi, Missouri, New Mexico, Ohio, Oklahoma, Tennessee and Texas. Other photographs document the Indian exhibits at the Panama-Pacific International Exhibition, 1915, and the Panama-California Exposition, 1915-1916. A scrapbook depicts Mexican scenes and individuals, as well as Southwestern Indians. Two guest register books are for Hermit's Rest, Phantom Ranch, and Hermit Creek Camp, at the Grand Canyon, 1922 to 1930. A ledger book records some Grand Canyon operations, 1906 to 1933. Blueprint plans for news stands are also included. Correspondence consists mostly of letters of commendation for services rendered to patrons. Many are written on menu cards or hotel stationery.
Photographs are arranged alphabetically by state, then city. Numbers within parentheses indicate number of photos.
Atchison, Topeka, and Santa Fe Railway Company; Hotel El Tovar; Fred Harvey (Firm); Panama-California Exposition (1915: San Diego, Calif.); Panama-Pacific International Exposition (1915: San Francisco, Calif.); Hotels -- United States -- Photographs; Railroad stations -- Food service -- United States -- Photographs; Restaurants -- United States -- Photographs; Hopi Indians -- Photographs; Navajo Indians -- Photographs; Indians of North America -- Southwest, New -- Photographs; Tourism -- West (U.S.) -- History; Exhibitions -- California; Grand Canyon National Park (Ariz.) -- Registers; Correspondence; Guest registers; Photographs
Container List
- Series I: Photographs, No Dates
  - Arkansas: Fayetteville (3). (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Arkansas: Fort Smith (3). (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Arkansas: Jonesboro (1). (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Arkansas: Rogers (2). (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Arizona: AshFork, Hotel "Escalante" (30). (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Arizona: Del Rio Farms (22). (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Arizona: Kingman (5). (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Arizona: Peach Springs (including one photo of the Santa Fe Dairy). (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Arizona: Phoenix (4). (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Arizona: Seligman (14). (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Arizona: Williams, "Fray Marcos" Hotel (39). (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Arizona: Winslow (20). (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Arizona: Winslow, "La Posada" Hotel (37). (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Grand Canyon, Arizona: Bright Angel Camp (20). (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Grand Canyon, Arizona: Hermit's Rest and Hermit Creek Camp. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Grand Canyon, Arizona: Hopi House (47, includes 2 photos of visiting celebrities Douglas Fairbanks and General Pietro Bagdoglio). (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Grand Canyon, Arizona: The Lookout (18). (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Grand Canyon, Arizona: Phantom Ranch (5). (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Grand Canyon, Arizona: Station and railroad yards. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Grand Canyon, Arizona: Campers Lodge, view, trail, etc. (8). (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Grand Canyon, Arizona: "El Tovar" Hotel - exterior (15). (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Grand Canyon, Arizona: "El Tovar" Hotel - interior (23) (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Grand Canyon, Arizona: "El Tovar" Hotel - Rendezvous Room (8). (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Grand Canyon, Arizona: "El Tovar" Hotel - accessory buildings, power house, laundry, garage, etc. (14). (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - California: Bagdad (1). (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - California: Bakersfield (9). (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - California: Barstow, "Casa del Desierto" (40). (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - California: Fresno (5). (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - California: Los Angeles, La Grande Station (14). (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - California: Merced (4). (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - California: Mojave (6). (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - California: Needles, "El Graces" Hotel - exterior (26). (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - California: Needles, "El Graces" Hotel - interior (37). (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - California: San Bernardino (24). (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - California: San Diego (18). (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - California: San Francisco, ferries and news agencies (7). (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - California: Stockton (4). (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Colorado: Colorado Springs (25). (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Colorado: La Junta (29). (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Colorado: Trinidad, "The Cardenas" Hotel (13). (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Illinois: Chicago, Dearborn Station (21). (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Illinois: Chicago, Englewood Station (1). (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Illinois: Chicago, Union Station - exterior (7). (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Illinois: Chicago, Union Station - waiting rooms (19). (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Illinois: Chicago, Union Station - train concourse (12). (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Illinois: Chicago, Union Station - dining areas and kitchens (25). (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Illinois: Chicago, Union Station - Shoppers' Mart (17). (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Illinois: Chicago, Union Station - Minute Shops (19). (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Illinois: Chicago, Union Station - barber shop, beauty shop, junction shop (12). (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Illinois: East St. Louis (7). (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Kansas: Arkansas City (3). (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Kansas: Augusta (2). (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Kansas: Chanute (13). (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Kansas: Dodge City, "El Vaquero" Hotel (15). (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Kansas: Emporia (19). (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Kansas: Fort Scott (3). (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Kansas: Hutchinson, "The Bisonte" Hotel (34). (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Kansas: Lawrence (3). (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Kansas: Newton (21). (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Kansas: Pittsburg (2). (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Kansas: Syracuse, "The Sequoyah" Hotel (18). (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Kansas: Topeka (10). (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Kansas: Wellington (11). (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Kansas: Wichita (12). (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Missouri: Cape Girardeau (4). (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Missouri: Joplin (6). (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Missouri: Kansas City, Union Station - exterior (16). (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Missouri: Kansas City, Union Station - lobby, waiting rooms (29, includes Red Cross and Liberty Loan Booths from World War I era). (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Missouri: Kansas City, Union Station - dining areas and kitchens (21). (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Missouri: Kansas City, Union Station - drug store (13). (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Missouri: Kansas City, Union Station - fruit, candy and toy shops (23). (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Missouri: Kansas City, Union Station - news stand, book shop, cigar stand (21). (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Missouri: Kansas City, news agency (3). (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Missouri: Monett (18). (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Missouri: Newburg (2). (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Missouri: Saint Louis, Union Station (18). (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Missouri: Saint Louis, news agency, news stands at Eads Bridge and Tower Grove (6). (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Missouri: Springfield (23). (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - New Mexico: Albuquerque, "The Alvarado" Hotel - exterior (11). (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - New Mexico: Albuquerque, "The Alvarado" Hotel - various interiors (12). (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - New Mexico: Albuquerque, "The Alvarado" Hotel - dining areas (21). (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - New Mexico: Albuquerque, "The Alvarado" Hotel - museum and Indian building (35). (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - New Mexico: Albuquerque, "The Alvarado" Hotel - Indian store room, laundry (13). (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - New Mexico: Albuquerque, "The Alvarado" Hotel - news stand, news agency (12). (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - New Mexico: Albuquerque, "The Alvarado" Hotel - events (25). (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - New Mexico: Belen (14). (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - New Mexico: Clovis, "Gran Quivira" Hotel (27). (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - New Mexico: Deming (8). (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - New Mexico: Gallup, "El Navajo" Hotel (53). (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - New Mexico: Lamy, "El Ortiz" Hotel (12). (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - New Mexico: Las Cruces (3). (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - New Mexico: Las Vegas, "Castaneda" Hotel. (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - New Mexico: San Marcial (5). (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - New Mexico: Rincon (5). (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - New Mexico: Santa Fe, "La Fonda" Hotel (17). (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - New Mexico: Vaughn, "Las Chaves" Hotel (6). (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Mississippi: Amory (1). (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Tennessee: Memphis (1). (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Ohio: Cleveland, Union Station - general (19). (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Ohio: Cleveland, Union Station - dining rooms and shops (35). (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Oklahoma: Afton (3). (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Oklahoma: Antlers (3). (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Oklahoma: Ardmore (6). (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Oklahoma: Bartlesville (3). (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Oklahoma: Claremore (2). (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Oklahoma: Enid (2). (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Oklahoma: Francis (3). (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Oklahoma: Guthrie (6). (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Oklahoma: Henryetta (3). (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Oklahoma: Hugo (10). (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Oklahoma: Madill (1). (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Oklahoma: Miami (2). (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Oklahoma: Muskogee (3). (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Oklahoma: Oklahoma City (10). (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Oklahoma: Okmulgee (3). (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Oklahoma: Purcell (2). (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Oklahoma: Sapulpa (20). (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Oklahoma: Snyder (6). (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Oklahoma: Tulsa (5). (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Oklahoma: Vinita (6). (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Oklahoma: Waynoka (9). (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Texas: Amarillo (18). (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Texas: Beaumont (2). (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Texas: Brownwood (10). (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Texas: Canadian (13). (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Texas: Cleburne (1). (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Texas: Dallas (4). (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Texas: El Paso (10). (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Texas: Fort Worth (13). (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Texas: Gainesville (1). (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Texas: Galveston (15). (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Texas: Houston (14). (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Texas: Paris (3). (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Texas: Rosenberg (4). (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Texas: Silsbee (6). (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Texas: Slaton (7). (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Texas: Somerville (1). (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Texas: Sweetwater (9). (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Texas: Temple (19). (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Panama-California Exposition, Painted Desert Exhibit, San Diego, California (32). 1915-1916 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Panama-Pacific International Exposition, Grand Canyon Exhibit, San Francisco, California (22). 1915 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous and unidentified photos (15). (Box 11, Folder 3)
    Includes photos of Jackie Coogan from a movie role and a photograph tentatively identified as Herman Schweizer with one of the Harveys.
  - Scrapbook of photos of unidentified persons, Grand Canyon, Indians, Mexico and unidentified places, possible compiled by Herman Schweizer (184). (Box 11, Folder 4)
    Postcards addressed to Herman Schweizer found in the scrapbook were processed with correspondence.
- Series II: Correspondence, 1896-1944
  - Correspondence. 1896-1915 (Box 12)
    Includes testimonial signed by Caruso, Sembrich and other members of the Conried Metropolitan Opera Company, April 15, 1906.
  - Correspondence. 1916-1921 (Box 13)
    Includes correspondence from William Jennings Bryan, August 11, 1920 and William Jennings Bryan, Jr., July 31, 1921.
  - Correspondence. 1922-1926 (Box 14)
    Includes correspondence from William Jennings Bryan, July 28, 1925, Howard Chandler Christy, December 9, 1925 and A. V. Kidder, August 30, 1926.
  - Correspondence. 1927-1930 (Box 15)
    Includes correspondence from Neil Judd while on a Pueblo Bonito Expedition, October 27, 1927 and from the Chicago Cubs while on a training trip to Catalina Island, February 13, 1928.
  - Correspondence. 1931-1935 (Box 16)
    Includes correspondence from Neil Judd, September 4,1931.
  - Correspondence. 1936-1942 (Box 17, Folder 1-6)
  - Motor Vehicles correspondence, financial and legal papers. 1925-1944 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Postcards to Herman Schweizer. 1908, 1910, 1915 (Box 17, Folder 8)
- Series III: Supplemental Material
  - Miscellaneous clippings. (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Promotional Photo Brochure. 1945? (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Hermit's Rest Register Book. January-May 1924 (Volume 18)
  - Hermit Creek Camp Register Book. August 1922-August 1930 (Volume 19)
    The register also includes records for Phantom Ranch, 1922-1928.
  - Fred Harvey News Stand Plans (an album of blueprints). (Volume 20)
  - Ledger: "Transportation Department, Grand Canyon, Arizona." 1906-1933 (Volume 21)
    Includes records for blacksmith and carpenter shops, bungalows, garage, livestock, Hermit Creek Camp, mess house, Phantom Ranch, various rest houses, etc.
  - Ledger. (Volume 22)
    Similar to volume 21.
  - Miscellaneous items. (Volume 23)